National Railway Labor Conference Additional Records 5205
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
National Railway Labor Conference Additional Records
1915-1936
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
National Railway Labor Conference
McAdoo, W. G. (William Gibbs), 1863-1941.
Hines, Walker D. (Walker Downer), 1870-1934.
5205
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Records accumulated by the Western, Eastern and Southeastern Carriers Conference Committees, which served as the collective bargaining units for the member railroads in their jurisdictions prior to the establishment of the National Railway Labor Conference.
8859605
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, April 1, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, April 01, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The National Railway Labor Conference [NRLC] was formed in October 1962 to represent the carriers in negotiations with railroad unions. Until 1962, the carriers negotiated through regional committees. They were the Western, Eastern, and Southeastern Carriers Conference Committees, which coordinated their positions in reaching industry-wide settlement. As the successor organization to these committees, the NRLC is in possession of numerous records of historic importance. As part of an initiative by Cornell University's ILR School to document the history of Railroad Industrial Labor history, the NRLC provided copies of some of their historic records from these committees. The majority of the copies were provided on microfilm, and may be found in collection 5205mf; thirteen bound, photocopied volumes are found in this collection.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1915-1936
Bulk dates: 1915-1936
This collection consists of thirteen bound, photocopied volumes produced by the National Railway Labor Conference.
Two volumes contain minutes of meetings from the Board of Arbitration between the Western Railroads and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen.
Nine volumes consist of reports to and from two Director General of Railroads of United States Railroad Administration, W. G. McAdoo and Walker G. Hines. Of interest in these reports are the sections dealing with home front mobilization for World War I, the need to employe women in the railroad industry, and the explicit statement that African-Americans and women receive the same wages as their white male couterparts in W. G. McAdoo's 1918 report to the president. In the reports of Walker G. Hines, there are more in depth statistics regarding the women employed by the railroads during their nationalization during World War I.
Two volumes are indexes of decisions affecting engine and train employees, created by the Bureau of Information of the Eastern Railways.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5205 mf: National Railway Labor Conference Records on Microfilm
Railroads--United States.; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Railroads -- United States; United States Railroad Administration.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Transportation; National Railway Labor Conference (U.S.)
8859605
- Minutes of Meeting of Board of Arbitration, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Reconvened At Chicago Illinois, August 17, 1915.
- Minutes of Meeting of Board of Arbitration, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Reconvened at Chicago Illinois, January 4th 1916.
- Reports, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: Report to the President by W. G. McAdoo, Director General of Railroads, 1918; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Report of the Work of the United States Railroad Administration for the first seven months of its existence, ending July 31, 1918
    Format: Pamphlet.
  - Item 2: Annual Report of W. G. McAdoo, Director of Railroads, 1918, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Division of Labor of the Railroad Administration
  - Item 3: Annual Report of the Regional Director for the Northwestern Region to the Director General of Railroads, 1918; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Reports, 1919; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Annual Report of Walker D. Hines, Director General of Railroads, 1919; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Division of Law
  - Item 2: Annual Report of Walker D. Hines, Director General of Railroads, 1919; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Division of Labor
  - Item 3: Annual Report of Walker D. Hines, Director General of Railroads, 1919; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Northwestern Region
  - Item 4: Annual Report of Walker D. Hines, Director General of Railroads, 1919; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Division of Public Service
- Reports, 1920; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Report to the President by Walker D. Hines, Director General of Railroads, 1920; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    For fourteen months ended March 1, 1920
  - Item 2: To The Editors of the Newspapers of the United States by Walker. D. Hines, 1920; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Index to decisions affecting employees in engine and train service, 1936; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Index and Supplement to Index